Eamon Grennan papers, 1964-2010
Emory University
Eamon Grennan papers, 1943-2010
Grennan, Eamon, 1941-
Manuscript Collection No. 1150
38.75 linear ft. (82 boxes), 1 oversized paper (OP), and 3 bound volumes (BV)
Papers of Eamon Grennan, Irish poet and professor, including correspondence, diaries, writings by Grennan, writings by others, teaching and lecture files, and printed material.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 2010.
Restrictions on Access
Special restrictions apply: Series 1: Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
Series 1: Due to privacy concerns, some materials in the series have been redacted.
Biographical Note
Eamon Grennan, Irish poet and professor, was born on November 13, 1941 in Dublin, Ireland, to Thomas P. and Evelyn Grennan. Grennan received a B.A. and M.A. in English from University College, Dublin, in 1963 and 1964 respectively. He lived in Rome from 1965-1966, then moved to the United States for graduate school. He received his Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1973. He married Joan Perkins, whom he met in Rome, in 1972. The couple had two children, Kate Grennan and Conor Grennan. They divorced in 1985. He subsequently met long time companion, classicist Rachel Kitzinger, with whom he has one daughter, Kira Grennan.
Grennan taught at Herbert Lehman College, City University of New York, from 1971-1974. In 1974, he accepted a position with Vassar College, where he taught English until his retirement in 2004. During a year's leave from Vassar in 1977, which he spent in Ireland, he began writing poetry seriously for the first time. Grennan published his first volume of poetry, Wildly for Days, in 1983. He has published numerous volumes of poetry since, including What Light There Is (1987), As If It Matters (1991), So It Goes (1995), Relations: New & Selected Poems (1998), Selected & New Poems (2000), The Quick of It (2005), Out of Breath (2007), Matter of Fact (2008), and Out of Sight: New and Selected Poems (2010). His What Light There Is and Other Poems (1989) was a finalist for a Los Angeles Times Book Prize, and Still Life with Waterfall (2002) won the Lenore Marshall Poetry Prize in 2003.
Grennan has also edited several volumes including New Irish Writing: Essays in Memory of Raymond J. Porter (1989), and Facing the Music: Irish Poetry in the Twentieth Century (2004). He has also translated numerous works by Italian poet Giacomo Leopardi, as well as an edition of Oedipus at Colonus (2004) on which he partnered with Kitzinger.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of the personal and literary papers of Eamon Grennan from 1943-2010. The papers include a small amount of correspondence and personal papers; writings by Grennan; writings by others; diaries; printed material; and photographs. Correspondence is limited, but includes editorial correspondence, letters from colleagues and other writers including Peter Fallon and Ann Roesnes, and personal correspondence from friends and family. Personal papers include biographical information about Grennan such as his curriculum vitae and bibliography, as well as appointment books and contracts.
Writings by Grennan form the bulk of the collection and include both Grennan's poetry and prose works, as well as notebooks, lectures, and teaching files. Writings by others consist of literary manuscripts sent to or collected by Grennan from other authors such as Louis Asekoff, Tom MacIntyre, and Desmond O'Grady. Also present are manuscripts of Grennan's translations of other authors' works. The diaries are personal in nature and chronicle Grennan's life and travels. Printed material contains copies of Grennan's published writings, promotional materials relating to his appearances and speaking engagements, and general printed material relating to other authors or topics of interest to Grennan. There are very few photographs in the collection and primarily consist of unidentified people and places.
Arrangement Note
Organized into six series: (1) Correspondence and personal papers, (2) Writings by Grennan, (3) Writings by others, (4) Diaries, (5) Printed material, and (6) Photographs.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Kitzinger, Rachel, 1948-; Fallon, Peter, 1951-; Asekoff, L. S. (Louis S.), 1939-; Heaney, Seamus, 1939-; Mac Intyre, Tom, 1931-; O'Grady, Desmond, 1935-
Corporate Names
Vassar College--Faculty.
Topical Terms
English poetry--Irish authors--20th century.; Irish poetry--20th century.; Poets, Irish--20th century.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts; Poems
Description of Series
- Correspondence and personal papers, 1961-2010, Series 1; Boxes 1 - 2, 82
  Scope and Content Note
  The series consists of Grennan's correspondence and personal papers from 1961-2010. The correspondence is limited but includes editorial correspondence, letters from colleagues and other authors including Peter Fallon and Ann Roesnes, and personal correspondence from friends and family. Personal papers primarily consist of biographical information about Grennan, as well as Grennan's bibliography and curriculum vitae, appointment books, and contracts.
  Additional editorial correspondence can be found in Series 2: Writings by Grennan.
  Arrangement Note
  Correspondence is arranged in chronological order. Personal papers are arranged in alphabetical order.
  Restrictions on Access
  Special restrictions apply: Series 1: Letters by Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers.
  Due to privacy concerns, some materials in the series have been redacted.
  - Correspondence
  - General correspondence, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence, 1964-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General correspondence, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General correspondence, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General correspondence, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General correspondence, 2005-2010 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence from Seamus Heaney, 1979-2004 [RESTRICTED] (Box 82, Folder 1)
  - Personal papers
  - Appointment book, 1961 October-1962 August (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Appointment book, 1965 May-1966 June (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Appointment book 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Appointment book, 1967 January-1968 January (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Appointment book 1967 June-1968 July (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Appointment book, 2005 December-2006 December (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Best American Poetry comment by Grennan on "The Curve" and biographical note, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bibliography, no date (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bibliography of publications by year, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Biographical sketch, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Biographical sketch, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Biographical sketch for "Eamon Grennan" by Joseph Lennon in The Encyclopedia of the Irish in America, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Contact list for poets, no date (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Contemporary Authors New Revision Series personal information for listing, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Contracts, 1987-2006 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Covering note to go with material submitted by Eamon Grennan to an unidentified publisher [includes curriculum vitae], undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Curriculum vitae, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Driver's license, New York state, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Invoices, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Payment schedule and information sheet for contributors to The Kenyon Review, no date (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Research, scholarship, and professional activities, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Schedule of readings and appearances [includes Greywolf Database contacts listing], 1998 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Redacted documents
  - Redacted documents [RESTRICTED] (Box 82, Folder 2)
- Writings by Grennan, 1962-2010, Series 2; Boxes 3 - 53; BV 1 - 3
  The series consists of writings by Eamon Grennan from 1962-2010, including poetry, prose, notebooks, and lecture and teaching files. The poetry series contains collected works, as well as uncollected, some of which were published in journals and magazines. Over the years, Grennan also maintained files containing drafts of his poems which he arranged in chronological order. This original arrangement has been preserved, though items may duplicate drafts found elsewhere in the subseries.
  The series also contains Grennan's prose writings such as essays, articles, reviews, short stories, and papers written while he was a graduate student at Harvard. Also present in the series are notebooks that contain both poetry and prose, drafts of invited lectures, material relating to poetry readings given by Grennan, and files from courses that he taught. Lecture files include drafts as well as reference material. Teaching files may contain syllabi, notes and assignments.
  Organized into five subseries: (2.1) Poetry, (2.2) Prose, (2.3) Notebooks, and (2.4) Lectures, readings, and teaching files, (2.5) Translations.
  - Poetry, 1962-2010, Subseries 2.1; Boxes 3 - 39
    The subseries consists of Grennan's poetry from 1962-2010 and is comprised of collected and uncollected poetry, as well as translations of Grennan's poetry by others. The collected poetry subseries (Subseries 2.2a) includes drafts of individual poems, draft typescripts of whole works, proofs, front matter, some editorial correspondence, and other materials relating to the publication process. The uncollected poetry and translations subseries (Subseries 2.1b) contains uncollected poems, some of which were individually published in journals and magazines. It also includes several French translations of Grennan's poetry by Michèle Duclos. The chronological poetry drafts subseries (Subseries 2.1c) consists of drafts of poems arranged chronologically by Grennan. Poems in this subseries may duplicate poems found in the subseries for both collected and uncollected poetry.
    Organized into three subseries: (2.1a) Collected poetry, (2.1b) Uncollected poetry, and (2.1c) Chronological poetry drafts.
    - Collected poetry, 1972-2010, Subseries 2.1a; Boxes 3 - 20
      The subseries contains poetry from published and unpublished collected works, as well as materials pertaining to the publication process. The collected poetry is arranged in chronological order by publication date and includes drafts of individual poems, as well as drafts of whole typescripts, proofs, front matter, and some editorial correspondence. Grennan frequently changed the title of a collection during the process of compiling and revising the typescript. Typescripts with these variant titles have been arranged in alphabetical order within each work, with different drafts in chronological order to the extent that could be determined.
      Most collected works also include working files that contain poems considered for publication in that work but which ultimately were not included. Some also include working files titled "Towards [work]," as labeled by Grennan. The original arrangement of these folders has been retained to preserve evidence of early drafting efforts. Many poems in the subseries have multiple drafts which may be located with typescripts of a complete work, working files, and the folder for that individual poem. Not all collected works contain all of these materials.
      The series also contains typescript drafts of other collected works, including unpublished works and small collections of poems published together in journals. Most of the unpublished works are from the 1970s, and were compiled by Grennan for personal reasons, such as to commemorate his wife's birthday.
      Collected works are arranged in chronological order, with folders arranged within each work as follows: poetry in alphabetical order; followed by all other folders in alphabetical order, with the chronological order of typescript drafts retained whenever possible.
      - Wildly for Days (1983)
      - "Armageddon Autumn" (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - "At My Sister's Flat in London" (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - "By the Hudson" (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - "Daughter Waiting for School Bus" (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - "Fall" (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - "For the Record" (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - "A Gentle Art" (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - "Gravechild, Renvyle" [Variant titles: "Persephone in Renvyle" and "Gravechild"] (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - "In Mount Auburn Cemetery" (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - "In the National Gallery, London" (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - "James Wright, 1927-1980" (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - "The Laundromat in Winter" (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - "Lying Low" (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - "Mother and Child" (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - "Muse, Maybe" [Variant titles: "Muse," "Muse Again," and "Musing"] (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - "Mushroom-Picking in the Old World" (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - "Night Driving in the Desert" (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - "On a 3.5 oz. Lesser Yellowlegs, Departed Boston August 28, Shot Martinique September 3" [Variant title: "On a Lesser Yellowlegs Shot in Martinique September 3, who Left Massachusetts August 28"] (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - "On a Cape May Warbler who Flew against My Window" (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - "Raeburn's Skater" (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - "Skunk" (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - "Something, After All" [Variant title: "Answer"] (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - "Speech" (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - "Stuffed Birds" (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - "Sunday Morning Through Binoculars" (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - "Swifts" (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - "Taking My Son to School" (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - "Trees After Snow" (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - "Wife" (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - "Winter" (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - The Book of Evasions [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft [Photocopy], 1982 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - The Book of Evasions [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - The Book of Evasions [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft [Photocopy with annotations] (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Coming to Attention [Variant title of Wildly for Days], poems considered for but not included in Coming to Attention (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Coming to Attention [Variant title of Wildly for Days], poems considered for but not included in Coming to Attention (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Coming to Attention [Variant title of Wildly for Days], towards Coming to Attention (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Coming to Attention [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Coming to Attention [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Coming to Attention [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft [Photocopy] (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Coming to Attention [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft [Photocopy with annotations] (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Coming to Attention [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - For the Record [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft [Photocopy with annotations] (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - For the Record [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - For the Record [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft [Photocopy with annotations, includes editorial correspondence] (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Wildly for Days, table of contents drafts (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Wildly for Days, typescript draft [Photocopy with annotations] (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Wildly for Days, typescript draft [Photocopy with annotations, includes editorial correspondence], July 9, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Wildly for Days, typescript draft [Photocopy, includes editorial correspondence] (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Witness [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft, late 1970s (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Witness [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft [Photocopy], late 1970s (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Witness [Variant title of Wildly for Days], typescript draft [Photocopy], late 1970s (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - What Light There Is (1987)
      - "All Souls' Morning" (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - "At Home in Winter" (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - "A Closer Look" (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - "Conjunctions" (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - "Daughter Lying Awake" (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - "Father in Front of a Picture" (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - "Four Deer" [Variant title: "Landscape with Figures"] (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - "Hieroglyphic" (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - "Homelight" [Variant title: "Homelight Homily"] (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - "Houseplants in Winter" (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - "Incident" (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - "Jewel Box" (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - "Lesson" (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - "Lizards in Sardinia" [Variant title: "Lizards"] (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - "Lunch-Break on the Edge of Town" (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - "Men Roofing" (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - "Morning: the Twenty-Second of March" (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - "Pieces of Kate" [Variant titles: "My Daughter Growing," "Daughter Growing," "Daughter in the Hands of Time," and "Collage of Kate"] (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - "Soul Music: The Derry Air" (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - "Staying in Bed" (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - "Totem" (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - "Traveller" (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - "Walking to Work" (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - "Walking Fall" (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - "Wing Road" (Box 5, Folder 25)
      - "Winter Morning: Twelve Noon" (Box 5, Folder 26)
      - "Women in Winter" (Box 5, Folder 27)
      - What Light There Is, table of contents drafts (Box 5, Folder 28)
      - What Light There Is, towards What Light There Is (Box 5, Folder 29)
      - What Light There Is, towards What Light There Is (Box 5, Folder 30)
      - What Light There Is, towards What Light There Is (Box 5, Folder 31)
      - What Light There Is, towards What Light There Is (Box 5, Folder 32)
      - What Light There Is, typescript draft, first (Box 5, Folder 33)
      - What Light There Is, typescript draft, second (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - What Light There Is, typescript draft, third [Photocopy] (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - What Light There Is, typescript draft, May 18, 1987 [Includes editorial correspondence] (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Twelve Poems (1988)
      - Twelve Poems, cover art material (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Twelve Poems, editorial correspondence (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Twelve Poems, front matter drafts [Includes editorial correspondence] (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Twelve Poems, news release draft (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Twelve Poems, towards Twelve Poems (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Twelve Poems, typescript draft (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Twelve Poems, typescript draft (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - What Light There Is and Other Poems (1989)
      - "Accidents" (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - "The Cycle of Their Lives" (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - "Eos" (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - "From Your Window" (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - "The Futility of Wishing" [Variant title: "Boy and Dog and the Futility of Wishing"] (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - "A Lack of Epitaphs" (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - "March" (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - "The Nature of America" (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - "Night-Piece" (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - "Patience in Renvyle" [Variant title: "Patience"] (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - "Porridge" [Variant title: "Under My Very Nose"] (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - "Vespers" (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - "Winn's Blackbird" (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - "Woodchuck" (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - What Light There Is and Other Poems, advance uncorrected page proof copy (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - What Light There Is and Other Poems, typescript draft, first (Box 6, Folder 24)
      - What Light There Is and Other Poems, typescript draft, second [Photocopy] (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - What Light There Is and Other Poems, typescript draft, third [Photocopy with annotations] (Box 6, Folder 26)
      - What Light There Is and Other Poems, typescript draft, fourth [Photocopy with annotations, includes editorial correspondence], December 13, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 27)
      - What Light There Is and Other Poems, typescript draft, fifth [Photocopy with annotations, includes editorial correspondence], January 24-27, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - What Light There Is and Other Poems, typescript draft, sixth [Photocopy with annotations] (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - As If It Matters (1991)
      - "Branchwater" (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - "Breakfast Room" (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - "Breaking Points" (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - "The Cave Painters" (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - "Compass Reading" (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - "Cows" (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - "Diagnosis" (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - "Driving Through Fog" (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - "Early Learning" (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - "Endangered Species" (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - "Family Sketches" (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - "Kitchen Vision" [Variant titles: "Visions" and "Two Views"] (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - "Leftovers" (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - "Moving" [Variant titles: "The Wife's Secret" and "Her Dream"] (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - "One Morning during the Elections" [Variant title: "One Morning"] (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - "Rights" (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - "Sea Dog" (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - "Small Mercies" (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - "Two Climbing" (Box 7, Folder 21)
      - "Two Gathering" (Box 7, Folder 22)
      - "Uphill Home" (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - "Walk, Night Falling, Memory of My Father" (Box 7, Folder 24)
      - "Walking Home as the Rain Draws Off" (Box 7, Folder 25)
      - "Woman at Lit Window" (Box 7, Folder 26)
      - "Woman Holding a Balance" (Box 7, Folder 27)
      - As If It Matters, cover design draft (Box 7, Folder 28)
      - As If It Matters, front matter drafts (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - As If It Matters, towards As If It Matters (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - As If It Matters, typescript draft (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - As If It Matters, typescript draft, December 21, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 32)
      - As If It Matters, typescript draft [Photocopy with annotations, includes editorial correspondence], November 4, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - For the Moment Standing [Variant title of As If It Matters], typescript draft [Photocopy] (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Tongues and Dust [Variant title of As If It Matters], typescript draft [Photocopy] (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - So It Goes (1995)
      - "Angel Looking Away" (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - "Ants" (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - "At the Falls" (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - "Bat" (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - "Birthday Walk with Father" [Variant titles: "Birthday" and "Birthday Father"] (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - "Border Incident" [Variant title: "Silence"] (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - "Bridge" (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - "Bubbles" (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - "Couple" (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - "Day's Work" [Variant titles: "Work" and "A Day's Work"] (Box 8, Folder 13)
      - "Firefly" (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - "From the Plane Window" [Variant title: "Flight"] (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - "Ghosts" [Variant title: "Ghost"] (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - "Glimpses" [Variant titles: "Rituals," "Father," "Father in Bits," "Bits of My Father," "Appearances," and "Glimpses of My Father"] (Box 8, Folder 17)
      - "Headlines" (Box 8, Folder 18)
      - "Heirloom" (Box 8, Folder 19)
      - "Heirloom" and "Shed" (Box 8, Folder 20)
      - "Horses" (Box 8, Folder 21)
      - "House" (Box 8, Folder 22)
      - "Journey" [Variant titles: "Journey to Her Death" and "Journey to My Mother's Death"] (Box 8, Folder 23)
      - "Night Figure" (Box 8, Folder 24)
      - "On Fire" [Variant titles: "Fire" and "Fire Gazing"] (Box 8, Folder 25)
      - "Outing" (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - "Passing Cold Spring Station" (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - "Pause" (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - "Shed" (Box 9, Folder 4)